Okay, you got it.
>> And it's seven 07. I'll call the Planning and Zoning Commission meeting to order.
First up on the agenda is roll call and seating of alternates.
I see Anne Cremay in attendance,
Steve Nelson,
Leanne Hutchinson,
myself, Scott Persson is absent.
And so next up on well, we also have alternates
Susan
England and Anne Blanchard present.
Next up in the rotation to be seated is
Susan England. So Susan,
you'll be seated as a commission member for tonight's meeting. I can't see it. Okay.
Jim, can you put yourself on mute while you're talking there?
Okay.
>> Eric, do you have the power to mute him until he gets
done talking there?
Okay.
>> That works. Okay.
Next up are additions or changes to the agenda.
And I have none. Does anybody else have any
additions or changes
to the agenda to
discuss?
I hear none. So, we'll move on to
item four on the agenda, public speak.
And
anybody
from the public have any comments that they would like to make before
we start this evening?
Okay,
hearing none, we'll move down to
old business.
And the first item up on the agenda is
the restoration of the permitted gravel pit
on Route 6.
And at this point,
we have nobody
here to address that issue with us.
And so I'm going to
defer that item for the
moment.
I
have nothing to update
item five beyond Rosewood Acres.
And so we'll go
on to item five see
the response to the letter
from
Jerry Gourmet.
And Eric, if you could allow me to share my screen.
Okay, you should be able to.
>> At the last meeting,
we discussed the letter from the
Board of Education Chairman, Jerry Cremay,
about
some concerns that the board had with respect to
the
proposed senior community center project.
I
think
I sent this letter out to all the commission members.
Steve, did you get that? Yes, I did. Okay.
So,
think
it certainly doesn't say much other than the fact that, you know, the chairman of the Community Senior Center Building Committee forwarded the concerns to the engineer
who is managing the project for the town of Andover.
We don't have an application at this point, and so
we thought that was the appropriate action to take.
>> But
at this point, I'll make a motion to approve
the draft letter to
the Board of Education from
the zoning enforcement officer and the Planning and Zoning Commission.
Second.
>> Okay, thank you, Steve. Any comments on the letter?
Hearing
none, I'll call for a vote on the motion. Anne?
Aye.
Steve?
Leigh Ann?
Aye.
>> Susan?
And I vote aye as well. The motion passes five-zero-zero.
>> Mr. Chairman, for the record Mark Brantz,
Commission Counsel, just one thing
for Mr. Hallisey.
Do not publish a legal notice of that vote.
It it is not an appealable decision,
and and I don't wanna open an appeal option for it.
That that the vote the vote you just took is is in the way of guidance of for concerning communication
and does not need a legal notice.
>> Okay, thank you Attorney Branch. Certainly.
Next we're going to move down to new business
>> Jed, it looks like Jim is back. Do you want to check on the gravel pit situation?
>> Jim, what did you and you're on mute, Jim.
Jim, you're still on mute.
>> Okay,
I spoke to Chris Bell. Yep.
He didn't seem to recall the meeting, but he will be on in a few minutes. So I told him
we would, when he gets on, we would
bring up his item as soon as possible. Okay.
>> Now, so we are into new business at this point, and I would like to start with
item
6C,
the request for filing extension.
Eric, if you can just run
us through what the purpose of your
request is just so that all the Commission members
understand what we're trying to do.
>> Yeah, So
back at the August meeting,
I presented
modifications
to
what
was a subdivision plan and a special permit
application
because
Eversource was requiring.
Was forcing me to move utilities to the other side of the property
that that had a much greater impact.
Then the original plan, So what they required of me was to
in order to have their engineer approve the plan.
The original utilities plan was to actually have a driveway come from the other side of our property.
That matter, the Commission was kind enough to to vote on that matter.
At that meeting and and approved with, you know, the conditions, including filing of mylars and and easements.
It has been,
I believe it's gonna be ninety days if it hasn't already passed
within the last day or two. But I submitted a letter requesting
an extension just because I've been,
no matter how much I seem to try to email or leave voicemails with the Eversource engineer,
I
haven't gotten contact from them, which has caused delays.
And then
my engineer
has also required
more time than I was thinking he would to get the the plans modified and the information that my attorney needs to
draft up easements and communicate with Eversource.
I am at the point where I have my LARS.
Right here in fact,
and my attorney
is in possession of the information that he needs.
What's outstanding, think it's just
my attorney, by the way, Stan Falkenstein.
He
has a little he has a little more work drafting agreements and then and then I believe he still needs to
get in touch with his his person at his counterpart at Eversource to get
to get the ball rolling there. But I think the the big logjam for me is kind of broken
and I'm hoping that in the next two weeks to three weeks, I'll have all that sorted out and I could
file everything
With the clerk.
>> So would there
need to be any changes made to the mylars that you have now
once the easement gets approved, or is that all the easement approval will put it in compliance with the mylars that you currently have in hand?
>> That's correct. Yeah, I I won't need new mylars. These these are final.
It's
just some it's just a matter of getting.
Driveway easement updated with the new
a new area that was that.
You
know that that my property
actually rather
my neighbor's property is going to require us to like go through.
So I wouldn't need any changes to the MYLARs. Think they're final copies.
>> Okay.
Agent Halsey, I know you and I had talked about the possibility
of
making a motion to change the previous
conditions of approval to support filing the mylars
without
>> Yes.
I thought as an alternative to
the extension
of the filing request, just simply change the conditions
to require that the easements be filed prior prior to the issuance of a build
building permits.
I would think
No. Yeah.
>> You don't? Yeah, for the record Mark Brantz, we can't do that.
Once that
MYLAR is filed
on the land records,
whatever easements it depicts,
it shows is it.
That's very risky. I've seen that happen before and it leads to bad things.
The extension of time is perfectly reasonable request, routinely granted,
Mr. And I won't
try to pronounce your last name but
has certainly provided a good explanation for why he may not meet the ninety
day filing requirement.
But when we have all the ducks together, and by the way does not require a commission meeting to endorse those that mylar,
the chairman can do that any old time,
So if he gets Eversource squared away
in a week or two weeks or whatever, he does not have to wait for the next commission meeting. The Mylar's can be endorsed at any time.
Thank you.
>> Okay, so with that in mind,
I'll make a motion to approve a ninety day extension for filing of the mylars on the Pine Ridge Subdivision.
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve.
Any discussion on that
motion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Steve?
Leigh Ann?
Aye.
Susan?
>> Aye.
And I vote aye as well. The motion
to extend the filing deadline for ninety days is approved.
I think that's
>> all you wanted from us tonight, Eric? Yes. That is it. I do see the note in the chat, is that from from Eric about the Eversource rep?
>> Yes. That is. So if you do have problems with it and you can't get it through, let me know, and I'll rattle our source rep
to to work on it.
Okay, thank you.
>> Attorney
Fullerkenstein
knows me well.
So when he has his documents for my review, we can work that out.
He knows where to find me.
Okay.
Thank you very much, Paul.
>> Okay, at this point, I'm going to work back to
item
6B,
receive application and set public hearing for various amendments to section five
Andover Rules of Design and section 24 definitions
of the Andover zoning regulations.
So it's allowed municipal land uses in the ARD subject to special permit.
I think I still got share screen permission, is that correct, Eric?
Okay, so before
I
jump over to the
proposed changes,
I sent out,
as I recall, sent out and I sent out a lot of things to the Commission within the last month this time,
but I think you saw the,
I forget what it's
called the petition to change the regulations I think it is so as we were working through the issues of the
community center
We discovered that
our regulations
as currently existing
>> tried the same way. If you go to the calendar
Thank you, Eric.
The
current regulations
didn't support putting in a
community
senior center.
And so we thought that maybe we should adjust the regulations
to
allow that.
Okay, so this
is my proposed
change to
Section five.
And going back,
Eric with Attorney Branch made several
recommendations
for changes
both
in Section five, the ARD,
Section seven,
the Lake District, Section eight,
I think it was either the
business district in section 24.
I was a little concerned with
all the things going on about
doing all those changes right now, but I certainly wanted to
amend
the
regulations as soon as we possibly could to facilitate
having the ability to
put a community center in the ARD,
which is where the town hall is located,
if we so chose to do that.
And so
this is the sections
that
Attorney Branch recommended that we change.
We deleted public parks, playgrounds,
athletic fields from here.
One of the things
that
Attorney Branch recommended,
and I think it has a lot of merit to it,
was we should be very careful
in what are the items that we have that
you can do in a district without a special permit.
You know, there was a bunch of surprise
that came up with a lot of people
when the Dollar General came to town that we didn't need to hold a public hearing for that and do the special
permit
with that, that all they had to do was comply with our regulations and a site plan review.
And so
one of the lessons,
well, that recommendation that Attorney Branch made
plus the experience of
Dollar General. And I guess the other one that comes to mind
is that when we were looking at
Scott Beebe's kennel application,
you know, that we were able to put through
because you could read the regs that a special
permit
and a public hearing were not required.
When I get around to changing that regulation, I will make it so that for any kennel,
a public hearing and a special permit is required because I think that's the right thing to do. So anyhow,
that's the basis of
what we've got here. So
up in the
permitted uses, we eliminated public parks, playgrounds and athletic fields.
Down in the special permit, we crossed out schools
and
put in municipal land uses.
We changed
5A02
to include houses of worship and cemeteries,
houses of worship in the place of churches and libraries because that would be included in the municipal land use item.
And then down here at the bottom, we took out private recreational areas and we put in the public parks, playgrounds,
and athletic fields.
And I know, Eric, you asked me a question at one time about
why did we eliminate
the private recreational
areas? Wouldn't we like to have those? And the answer comes back
is the way that we define public parks, playgrounds, and athletic fields would encompass
any of the items that
would be open to the public,
so private recreation areas
would probably not be required there.
So anyhow,
those are the changes
to
Section
five
that were recommended by
Attorney Branch and requested by
Eric Anderson
for the Planning and Zoning Commission.
Any questions or
comments on any of those changes?
Okay, and I do think they were fairly
straightforward at that point.
So, we can't approve those yet.
Changes will have to go to a public hearing before we can approve them and
agent Halsey
needs to send those out for some other local municipality
review.
And I think,
I forget how many days that review
we're required to give, but it ends up being that
the first time that we can
have a public hearing to vote on the changes would be in our
January meeting,
I think is
January 21 or
January 23.
It's a week later than normal due to the
Martin Luther King holiday.
So I'll make a motion that we set a public hearing for January 23 to discuss
the proposed changes to Section five ARD.
Second the motion.
>> Thank you, Steve.
Eric, did you have a comment? Saw that one moving forward.
>> I was just remembering your in your legal notice that
the these amendments affect more than just section five. I Miller we added a definition so there are other sections are involved.
We'll get to section 24 specifically.
Okay. All right. Yeah, no problem.
>> I have no comment other than I just want this expedited
to the extent that we can.
But I understand we need to
notify surrounding municipalities
and notify the COG, so it's not going to be overnight.
Okay.
Any other discussion?
>> Chad, in addition to Section 24, you also mentioned changes to Section seven and eight at a later date.
Will that be prior to the public hearing?
>> That will not be.
So
my goal for the public hearing, and we're going to talk about it a little bit here tonight,
is I would like to
make these changes which allow the community center
the changes to definitions
which support,
I think it was
municipal land uses and public
something or other, we'll get there in a minute.
And then the third item that I was going to try and squeeze in there, if we get through that without too much discussion tonight,
is the accessory dwelling units.
And so,
you know, we have opted out of accessory dwelling units in entirety from what was in the public act,
but the portion
that we specifically
wanted to opt out of was for the Lake District.
I've got some things to discuss that we might want to change with our other regulations
and just make sure we're where we want to be on that because I think that's an important issue for the affordable housing
discussion
and we'll go with that.
But anyhow, back to the motion. Well, other
>> discussion? Good. I have one comment and I may have missed it. I apologize. I was on the phone with Chris Bell trying to get up to the meeting. But I'm treating this as any
zone change amendment,
amendment to the text, and there's an application.
So what I had what I had put on the agenda was to receive the application
and set public hearing.
So I'm suggesting that you act to receive the application
prior to the public hearing. Okay.
>> So I will modify the motion
to include accepting
the application
and
setting the public hearing date for January 23.
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve. First, we'll vote on the modification
to the motion.
Any other discussion on the modification?
And I would put that up,
but I'm afraid I ran out of space on my computer to
put things down. And if I go back to the website here at this point, that might or might not work.
And it was pretty straightforward. Eric asked us to take a look at changing these couple of things
it's online if you care to look at that.
But hearing no other
discussion,
the motion is to modify
the initial motion.
And I'll call for a vote.
Anne?
Aye.
Steve? Aye.
Leanne?
Aye.
>> Susan?
Aye. And I vote aye as well.
The modification
of the motion passes five-zero-zero.
And now we go back to the entire motion as modified,
which is to receive the application to change the
regulations in section five
and set a public hearing date for January 23.
Any other last minute discussion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Steve?
Leanne?
Aye.
>> Susan?
Aye. And I vote aye as well. The motion passes five zero zero.
Thank you, commission members, for considering this.
>> Oh you're welcome.
Do you see Chris Bellum? I do see Chris Bell. I just,
since we're in the middle of
six
6b,
I'm going to call up the changes to the definitions
and
go through those couple of changes
and then we'll get on to the gravel.
Okay.
So we added,
here we added a municipal land uses.
And
I think I sent these out to everybody. Is that Yeah.
Okay. One of the many things I sent you out, so I won't read that.
And then we put
public buildings,
structures, uses which are open to the public owned by under the exclusive control of nonprofits,
social,
compared to municipal land uses. So if it isn't a municipal land uses, it's a public.
If it isn't a public, it goes back to being a municipal land use.
>> Mr. Chairman, for the record, Mark Brains, let me just also point out that this I know that for years we've needed to do a comprehensive revision of Andover
but you also have a definition of something called private recreation areas private recreational areas. Yep.
And that's there but that's defined
to be an accessory use
so that's why we're adding this pump new definition because that could be a principal use.
>> Okay
And just so,
while we're talking about the definition section here,
in a later presentation,
I have come up with the definition for the word frontage.
We've wrestled with that before.
And I was going to include that in this update
and I forgot.
And so, I still intend to
include that. We'll go through discussion, and if we can get agreement on what the
definition of frontage is later tonight,
I will include that in here before Jim sends it off for the
municipality
review,
and that would be included in our
public
hearing on January 23 as well.
So,
with
all that in mind, I'll make a motion to receive the application and set a public hearing for Section 24 of the definitions
with the public hearing to be held on January 23.
Second the motion. Thank you, Steve. Any discussion on
the definitions?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote.
Anne?
Aye.
Steve? Aye.
Leigh Ann?
>> Aye.
Susan?
Aye.
And I vote aye as well. So, we've received the public
we've received the application and set the public hearing for January 23. Thank you, everybody.
At this point, I'd like to go back to old business
item
5A, respirations permitted gravel pit
at 517
Route 6.
And Chris, I will turn it over to you at this point.
Let
>> us know where we stand. Okay, Mr. Chairman and Commissioners, I'm sorry. I
forgotten that Jim told me you want me at the meeting. I guess I forgot a lot of lot of things when I was in the hospital.
I have to tell you
about every fifteen seconds.
The audio cuts out on me. I can't hear what you're saying for about fifteen seconds, then it comes up.
I can tell when you're talking because your lips are moving, but I hear nothing.
All I can do is if I notice that you're talking and I can't hear you, I'm gonna have to say, I can't hear you, the audio cut out. I keep getting warnings that my internet connection is unstable,
for Anyway, some
let me try to be quick about this then.
We can hear you fine, Chris. Yeah. I know I think you're gonna hear me, but you may be cutting out on me. Okay. So,
I talked to the contractor and the owner today,
And I did talk to them also,
last week. And for some reason, they stopped the grading.
They said they had other stuff to do when they weren't sure
if they're going to be able to finish it right away but they're going to start again tomorrow I told them to take the high point out and make the low point because that's basically what they have to do that conform to the plan.
And the low point material
can be easily
spread to
the back towards the the sloped area, and that needs to be filled a little bit and then
filled towards
towards the access road which you know they still need to fill in a little bit more there
and stop at the floodplain line as,
as we had on the proposed plan.
They should be able to do that within a few days.
I don't think that's going to take very long.
And I think we can get an inspection on the rough grading as you know, we agreed to do it. Think I can do a video inspection because I know the grade stakes are out there.
He can take some laser shots while I'm on the
on a video with him.
And then once I'm happy with the grades, we can call Jim Helicy to come out and we can do a video conference.
And I'm sure the grades will be correct by the time we get out there.
At that point,
I think it's way too late in the season
to try to do topsoil
and then seed
because I know the seed is not going to take, it'll provide some erosion protection to hay, but I think we should wait for the spring, the topsoil and seeds, and then we'd be very successful and get a good crop of grass.
I mean, when the grading is done,
there's virtually,
you know, all the water is going be going towards the center for, you know, a good 75%
of the site. And the only thing will be left is what's along the floodplain along the access road, which, you know, always went towards the right anyway.
And we'll have to just keep and maintain those silk fences that, you know, there is a little bit of a low point in the access road that, you know,
it keeps breaking through. And we'll just have to keep monitoring
that over the winter to make sure that we don't get too much silt material going past the silt fence. Again, it's just sand.
But I would like to finish the grading.
I mean, do the topsoil in the spring. I
think the the contractor agrees that it would be much more successful.
Again,
all the drainage is going to go towards the center.
So
when it's finally completed,
and so we'll stay on that to make sure that's finished.
After that, I guess if you've got any other comments or thoughts, let's
talk.
>> Can hear My
first comment is I was disappointed
that we didn't get done by the November 17
after you asked for and we gave you two months to do the restoration?
>> Well,
was disappointed too.
I, you know, I wanted them to stay on it and they just just didn't.
And I I didn't have any control over that.
You know, I thought they were gonna finish up and call for an inspection and and they didn't. When I found out they never finished,
I wasn't too happy about that and they just never got back out there.
And I I I
don't know what to say. I I don't you know I can only
pound my fist so much. The owner was the same way he was trying to get them out there, but they had other jobs to finish. And I
wasn't happy about that at all.
Okay. No,
>> I understand that.
The other concern I had was,
and it sounds like
you had little control over this probably as well,
but we agreed when we agreed to the restoration plan that
you and Agent Halsey
and the
person doing the excavation were going to get together
forty eight hours prior to actually starting the excavation so that we could make sure that what was going to be done was
>> done in accordance with the plan. Yeah, and we did have an inspection
and everything was,
you know, all the hills were taken down except
they had a high point in the middle and we we did have an inspection with that and and with Jim
and I thought they were going to proceed. But right after that time it was only a week later that I had my accident, and basically I
was not really available to stay on top of it.
I only you know I took Jim's calls I tried to get things going but
apparently
I don't know their thoughts where they said, well, I'm not there, how are they going to get an inspection anyway and I guess they just left, which I was not very happy with at all.
And they never, even though I tried to get them before the seventeenth to get out there. It just didn't happen. I don't
know what else to say about it, you know, did the best I could but I couldn't control them at all. And either could the owner he was trying to get them out there too.
And
so
we're kind of stuck with, it's almost done but you know they can,
they can finish it, you know, in the next few days and get, get the low point in and that's about it, I guess, now.
>> Chris, do you know if if the erosion and sediment control measures
had been restored?
>> Yeah,
it was restored last week, actually.
That's what the the older told me had somebody go out there the day after Jim sent his notice.
And I was told they were finished in a, I think they're going to have to just, you know, try to triple that up because,
you know, we know where the weak point is, and I think they're just going to have to reinforce
it some more to last for the winter. I
mean, that's, it's only, it's only coming through basically one point.
And, you know, that's where,
well there's more drainage going there now because we have a high point once we take the high point out of there,
know,
than two thirds of that drainage is going to go towards the new low point.
It's going to be reduced quite a bit.
And,
>> go ahead. So what is different this time where we have a promise to be done within the next couple of days that's different than the last year?
>> Well,
they weren't intending to get back to do the granting until the end of September, which they did start then.
And they were on it for quite a bit for a while.
And unfortunately they just stopped short of the finish line.
I'm sure nobody's happy about.
I think I had a lot to do that I just
was not able to stay on top of it for the couple weeks I was in
bad part of the hospital. I just wasn't
there to get going on it to keep it up. I understand that.
Unfortunately, I'm the only one that seems to be pushing on it. The owner does, but he can't
get the contract to go out there as, you know, as much as he would like to. We're still kind of a victim to a contractor schedule, so.
>> Yep, and I think, you know, we have seen,
I've seen people
working on excavation over there probably
two days out of the last two months, maybe I missed one or two,
but it certainly hasn't been very much. In the contrast
with
that to what happened to the Dollar General across the street
that went to open for business in about two months after they started
is
incredible. So I don't know if the owners got the wrong
excavator
doing
that
or whatever. To
>> be all fair, Mr. Chairman,
building a building and starting a business is a money making operation.
This whole operation was a money losing operation for the owner.
He lost a lot of money just getting this done.
So,
unfortunately,
you know, everything, everything was going very fine until it just stopped. Mean, they were, they were really close to finishing it. Then I was actually surprised they never put the low point in after I got back to it after my surgery and I wasn't too happy about it. I thought they were going to finish that up with no problem, but they never went back. And then now they're on-site
ready to finish it. It's
just,
I mean,
I can't make excuses for the contractor. He just didn't show up. You know, they they go on to other priorities and they show up when they want to.
Unfortunately, it's for a job like this. It's it wasn't it's not a money making job for him either. He just made a deal with
Bill to finish it.
You know, he got very little material out of it. He was pretty much as a break even. So
unfortunately, it's still got to get finished.
And
I told him today that, you know, be really, it's really important to get that low point in just just to get the whole situation stable.
Bill's got to monitor that weak point in the sill fence. That's where all the water goes. Not right now,
which is kind of where the level spreader was.
>> Okay. And Chris, you saw the copy of the letter that
Mr. Genovese received
from Agent Halsey?
Yes, I did. I saw that.
Okay.
>> So that's the reason we invited
Attorney Branch here tonight is because
last time,
you know, we got into a similar
situation
here and
unfortunately
it took the threat of legal action
to
get the project back on track when we had the first extension authorized and we looked at what we had done and what we said we were going to do and they were significantly
different.
Attorney Branch, I would like the way ahead to be
that we give the applicant,
for which we have no application currently, I guess, we give the applicant until the end of the month to have
the
grading properly
restored. I guess we recall the primary grading.
Yeah, the grading done and
Oh, the audio is kicked out. I can't hear anything.
Say again, Chris.
You said the audio can't Okay, hear
well,
>> you may want to turn his video off, it might help with the feed.
>> That's probably a good idea. Chris, if you turn your video off, that might help your bandwidth.
All right, that's something I would know.
Stop video?
>> Yep. Yeah.
Okay,
so
let us know if you can't
>> anything.
Now the video is frozen. We can't. Everybody's frozen.
>> Okay,
then I will have agent Hallasteek brief you tomorrow on what we agreed to tonight.
But Attorney Branch,
my desire for the way ahead would be to have
the site graded in accordance with the
restoration
plan by the end of this month. That recognizes we've got Thanksgiving coming up at the end of this month here.
And at our next meeting in December, we have an updated restoration
plan
that includes action to
put in
the topsoil,
finish grading
and seeding at some point next
spring and whatever further actions it takes to bring
it into full compliance
with the restoration plan that
we were unable to achieve
by November 17.
>> For the record, Mark Brantz,
sounds like a
reasonable, very reasonable
goal to set,
but here's the problem we have:
the permit has expired,
the applicant has not filed an application
>> to renew the permit or to obtain a new one. And I can tell you why, Attorney Brantz, we're not excavating
and taking material off-site.
It's when we no longer have a gravel pit permit to remove material.
>> It it it makes Basically, we're no difference with the materials being removed or not. There is still grading activity occurring. And pursuant to the per the permit was to be was to be
the the permit required restoration.
The commission gave sixty more days to do the restoration. It hasn't been done. And I understand why, mister Bella. You've you've explained that. I I understand your your your situation.
But, we're
in the predicament now
where there is no permit.
The audio And the extension has been Excuse me, mister Bell. Mister Bell.
We are now in a situation where there is no permit.
The permit has expired, where the restoration period has expired, and the
Commission has no request before it or application before it to do anything further.
There is a way to solve this and the way to do that, my recommendation would be
that the zoning enforcement officer
issue an order
that incorporates
what you've just said Mr. Chairman, that incorporates
end of the month to
bring the grading into compliance,
whatever period in the springtime for looming, seating, and so on, immediate repair of E and S, which appears to have already occurred, at least Mr. Bell believes it's occurred.
That order would then authorize
the applicant
to proceed
without a permit because it's it's basically re it's a remediation
order.
That order would be filed in the land records,
which I think make sure that some innocent buyer does not acquire this property without knowing that there is an outstanding violation, which there is, and there will be an outstanding violation until spring at the rate we're going because you can't see, as Mr. Bell says, can't see it anymore.
It won't take.
And
I think part of that order should be,
the posting of a new bond,
in the amount of the loaming and seating to be to be sure that that when when when we inspected that and I was on the site Mr. Bell,
when we inspected that site it was questionable as to whether the required two inches of loam was even on the site.
Part of that order should be the posting of a new bond to assure the
grading, loaming,
seeding,
mulching
as required by the regulations.
What that will do is
that order, like I said, first of all, it will give authority
for the owners to do what it is they're supposed to be doing.
It will also assure that we don't get an innocent buyer
unaware of the situation.
Lastly,
if this does not happen,
if our contractor decides to,
pursue greener pastures once more,
then,
the violation of that order will by itself
trigger a $2,500
civil penalty,
against the owner,
and lay the groundwork for a civil suit against the owner for injunctive relief.
And
certainly understand the problem with contractors. They're all busy,
but the Commission has to have some
response to this. This seems to be the fairest and the most efficient way to handle it.
>> Any comments from the commission on what we just heard from attorney branch?
Jed?
Yes Leanne.
>> Yes
I
like the idea of going to but not beyond the end of the month
because I think we need to bear in mind as has been said that this is the end of the extension.
It's not the beginning of it's not a request for an extension. It's the end of an extension that was granted
and not much has been done.
And it doesn't seem like the owner is very active. And I don't think that
having the contractor
not be making much money doing this that could go on indefinitely.
It has gone on for quite a while and not much has been done since the last meeting.
So I think it's a good time frame to give them time to do something more,
but also not have this go all winter.
Can I ask a question of Jim?
Mr. Bell I think said that the erosion and sedimentation
control measures were fixed.
I think he said, I hope he can hear me
with his cutting in and out, the day after this letter was dated. So Jim, have you been able to go out there and check on the silt fences?
>> I was out there today, and I thought
that the silk fence in the far corner was was
not supported properly, but I'm gonna I'm gonna go back out. Other than that, it was it looked good. Yes.
It
it sometimes has kind of blown out from the back, and it's it's gotten to the point where it's hard to to maintain.
So
I will take a closer look at that, and it it may involve moving it forward or replacing
it with with hay bales or something of that nature.
It's just
it seems to have been a struggle to maintain throughout that throughout the course of work.
>> Mr. Allisworth again for the record Mark Brantz in
fashioning your order after
you do that inspection we can fine tune that so if there are things that need to be done with the E and S that can be part of your order as well with its own separate deadline.
>> Okay just for the record I will coordinate the springtime
seating with Hank Kruener who has
been very active on this project with respect to turtles.
Turtles on-site I believe that's a June issue, so I don't think it's a problem. I just want to double check.
>> And Leanne, just to
add on to your concern there or
mitigate it hopefully.
Dirty Branch's
recommendation
to include
a copy
of the order
in the file for the property.
As I understand,
Mr. Genovese is
anxious to
market
the property soon and having that
order, if it's not
complied with
in the file,
hinder anybody's
desire to go out and
purchase that property
at that point. So I think that provides
good motivation
too.
>> Okay, well that's I mean
I think that's helpful although he doesn't seem to have been too incentivized
so far
but
hopefully
that will help and if it comes to, you know, with this short timeframe,
again, is at the end of an extension that's already been granted,
he may just need to come up with somebody else who's more ready to do the work that we need done and it's been outlined very well.
Exactly.
Okay.
>> Attorney Branch, I'm Mr. Chairman, may I make
a comment?
Is that Chris? Mr. Chairman, may I make a comment?
Yes. I have no audio right now.
Hello?
>> You might
try doing, Chris, is calling into the phone number.
>> Well I I can hear him, I can hear I can hear Mr. Bell. Yeah you can hear me but that whole after I stopped speaking I heard probably about 10%
of the conversation. I I really don't,
I mean I heard that you want a new bond,
>> I heard a few words. I haven't heard most of the conversation. No. Jim Helichy will will get a hold of you tomorrow, Chris, and and go through everything.
>> I apologize
for I
don't know what I'm doing with this, but I
just like to say there
is, I mean,
any erosion that's occurring
is
basically on his
land,
and
the amount of water that's going
to the right is basically less than it was before
the site was done.
I mean there's no harm doing
to anybody except himself,
by not getting the project finished.
He's not hurting his neighbor.
It probably is nice to be if it was all done. I agree.
But,
you know, at this point, the owner is gonna know, you know, what is what is the problem. You know, it's my site, I'm trying to finish it,
and he doesn't understand why the town is so concerned about finishing it when the only harm that's coming to him is just an
untopsoiled
site with no grass on.
And I just wanted to let you know what his feeling was. He would like to get it done as soon as possible because then he could, you know, get someone to rent it or buy it. So it's it's not not because he doesn't want it to happen. He does. But
he's having a hard time getting it done. And
>> that's all I all that, Chris. And and I do think there is some detriment to having
the water
run down
to the east the
way it is.
I'm not sure that it's great to have all that water running down into the wetlands there.
And if we had graded the property
as
the restoration plan
specified,
we would have significantly minimized that runoff,
minimized that erosion,
and minimized the water going into the wetlands.
Think those are all things Well, it is wetland.
And that does not mean that we want all the water to be running down there.
In fact, that would be rationale for not having the water run down there
because it's not soaking into the ground.
>> Well, it is a type
A soil. Most of the water goes into the ground and doesn't doesn't run off,
but there is runoff II agree. There's no doubt about it.
And II think he at least controls the the
silt fences and
keeps the sand from going beyond the silt fence.
And,
you know, we shouldn't be able to control that over the winter.
I'll,
I'll note your comments that I did hear and tell him he's gotta
get this thing done ASAP.
>> Thank you. And Jim,
you'll
be able to
provide the order to Mr. Genovese,
route that through Attorney Branch before you send it to him just so we can get his cut on what you're sending out? Yes, I will. Okay. And I'll be in the office all day tomorrow. Mr. Chairman?
Yes, Ms. Hutchinson.
>> This is Catherine Hutchinson.
I respectfully request permission to be heard.
Go ahead.
>> I agree with you. I am, of course, particularly concerned
with that runoff
and Mr. Bell's comment that when the work is done that he's anticipating be done, two thirds of the water will be redirected.
The
restoration
plan
called for a 100% of it to be redirected,
>> not No, just two thirds of
that's not true.
That's not true. Well, the water that's in the floodplain, I can't stop Chris, Stop. I can't Okay. Do
>> The way you briefed us on the restoration plan
was that the
elevation
on the east side of the property
was going to be higher
than the high point elevation
on the west side of the property.
So, if the detention basin
filled up,
the excess was going to flow down towards the Extremart
and back towards the Hop River.
That was the discussion we had.
And so
understanding
that, I conclude that Ms. Hutchinson's comment is correct. We did agree
that the runoff was going to run down the west side of the property.
There's no audio.
>> Okay,
well, I
think we have the input we need from
Mr. Bell to decide the course of action.
And
I don't think at this point there's
any further action for the Commission
until we have Agent Halsey send out the order. And next month, we'll look forward to seeing the
updated restoration plan, And we will vote on that at that point.
Any other comments? Have no audio.
>> Again, this is Catherine Hutchinson. Continue to have have no no permission to speak. I appreciate it.
>> Oh, you're welcome. So any other comments on
on the gravel pit?
>> I only have one
to make 100% of the water flow towards the middle. I'd have to fill the access road in the floodplain I can't do that.
Understand that
and
>> and that's not what we're talking about. Okay. I just thought I thought you were talking about.
>> Mister chairman, for the re Mark Branch, what we're talking about is compliance with the the approved grading plan.
Correct. Whatever it shows, that's what it shows. Yep. Correct. Maybe it's two thirds. Maybe it's 90%.
Maybe whatever whatever it is, that's what it is. Correct.
Correct.
Okay.
So, that
completes item 5A.
>> Thank
you, Commissioner. Can't hear you anymore, but thank you. Thanks, Chris.
>> Next
item of business,
an attorney branch, you're welcome to stay. I think that
you have concluded.
We appreciate your help and support on coming up with the way ahead and
you're certainly welcome to stick around.
>> If you don't need me,
will sign off and
I'm going to shoot an email to Jim just with sort of summarizing what is my understanding of the order. Okay. Before you sign off,
>> Mark, I'll just mention to the Commission
to put the date March 11, I think it is. Yes.
Your calendars, that is going to be the next
session. I think March 11 is a Saturday.
Correct. Probably the better part of a Saturday
is the Connecticut Bar Association
training that
I attended two years ago. I thought it was excellent.
Attorney Branch has a big role to play in getting
that
to us, but
we as a commission do have requirements
going forward that we receive training.
This might not make all those wickets, but it will certainly
help you understand
the
roles, responsibilities,
and all those things associated with
the Planning and Zoning Commission. So I highly recommend if
you can take the time to attend that.
>> And it will be as two years ago it will be virtual. It used to be held in Wesleyan
and we had to cap it at 02:50 because even with an overflow room that
was all the room we had.
Two years ago we had six fifty signed up for it
and we responded to over 150 questions during that session.
So,
it's a packed day
covering public hearing procedures, non conforming uses, zoning regulation adoption, plan of development.
Every topic you've ever faced or ever will,
and the book is a
few 100 pages,
and as usual the Bar Association subsidizes this. Basically,
I forget the fee is probably going to be about 25 or $30 like last time, and that's just the printing cost of the book. The printing and mailing of the book is it. Everything else we cover.
So definitely March eleventh, Saturday, put on your calendar. Thank you for mentioning that, Mr. Chairman. Yep. And we have money in the budget to support
>> paying for the training so it'll be no cost to any of the Commission members that
attend that.
All right, have a happy Thanksgiving all.
Same to you, Dirty Branch.
>> By the way, I put January 23 on my calendar just in case if need be. Reserved that for you. You. Alrighty. Take care all. Bye bye.
Thanks, Mark.
>> Next item up is the
request for proposals for the upcoming plan of conservation
and development.
And that is this document here that I put up. I've sent that out to
everybody.
At this point, you know, I was
looking for feedback
on
So,
area down here, public input is desired to understand what type of housing people Andover are looking for,
whether the town should be encouraging growth, what type of growth the town desires, and what the taxpayers are willing to pay a little more taxes to achieve,
among other things.
Those were some questions
that I think the long term planning committee
asked
back in 2018.
This will be about five years later, but I think that
it would be good to get some input
from the folks from the town of Andover.
And so, this point, you know, my question for the Commission is, are there any other specific items that we should include in
this request for proposal
for
soliciting help to put that document together?
>> I don't have any suggestions at this time but I did notice
in the first or second paragraph there when you talk about bids
due by Wednesday
you
The date is missing. I think it's January 18. Oh,
>> idea.
And I had to work the timeline out on this to work it backwards.
My goal is to
get this out by
don't know what that was.
Didn't know was ready.
>> That was the goal.
Mid December so that
we can
have,
I think I put a
>> I think it says January 18 at the bottom. January 18, yeah. So
>> publication
date
twelveone.
Thanks for pointing that out to me, Steve. I'll put
an appropriate
date back
in there where I think we can actually get it out.
But one of the early weeks in December is what I'm shooting for,
assuming that I can work with Eric to get this out and
get
a reasonable turnaround where,
you know, it's, I think it's a pretty
considerable job, might take a little prep work on somebody's part to put in a bid for that. So thanks for the hint that
I need to fill in that blank.
Okay,
if there's no other discussion, I think that
wraps up
the plan of conservation and development.
Next
item up was
the accessory apartments.
And so
I had a couple of questions for the Commission to discuss.
And
we'll talk about the first item more in just a minute. I went through the definitions.
Should we use net or gross floor area? Our current regulations use gross floor area. The state recommendation
had net floor area.
And we'll
talk about that a little more in just a minute.
My assumption is whatever we pick,
probably what would happen
is,
at least when I've experienced these, I go to the assessor's cards
that have both a net floor area and gross floor area listed.
I don't know if those are based on our definitions or not, quite honestly,
but I think that that would be the most likely source of information that, you know, it's coming from the town and we would probably, if the card says X number of square feet,
we probably ought to go with that. That's the easiest,
most consistent thing that we can do there.
Our current regulations talk about an accessory apartment of between at least two fifty square feet up to
800 square feet.
And
I think the feedback I've gotten from Attorney Branch is that it is no longer legal
for us to specify
the minimum size of a house.
And so with that in mind, I figured we should not have a minimum size
for an accessory apartment.
The accessory apartment meets
the requirements that it has
a kitchen area,
facilities,
living space,
and you can do that in 100 square feet, more power to you.
You know, you're going to be deciding,
you know, does anybody want to come in and rent that or whatever.
Right now, we
should determine a maximum size. Our regulations are 800 square feet. I'm okay with that. State recommended 1,000.
We'll talk about that a little bit more going through. I think these numbers rarely come into play
because
both the state and our current regulations
talk about
either
30% or 33%
of the
floor space of the house. And so if you have a thousand square foot house,
that would give you a maximum
accessory apartment size of three thirty square feet.
So you never get close to that. You would have to have a 3,000 square foot house to come up with the 1,000 square foot accessory apartment.
And then the last question I had is, we care about the minimum lot size outside of the Lake District? You know, when we opted out,
we
opted out because we were
concerned about the quality
of the water quality of the lake
with the small lots and the septic
and all that.
I have recently discovered after
some discussions with Jim on 12th Center Street, and I went looking back at the lots there, there are some very small lots in the Town Center area.
In fact, there's a house on a lot, at least according to our town records,
where the lot is point zero eight acres in size.
Do we want to put further restrictions on an accessory apartment in that area or do we want to
allow the
health district,
you know, if it complies with the health requirements,
so be it. And
so those are some things to consider as we have a little conversation
about that now.
This just compares a little bit
our regulations between two fifty and eight hundred square feet or less than 33%
of the gross floor area of the single family dwelling.
The state said
not less than 30% of the net floor area or 1,000 square feet, whichever is smaller, whichever is less.
I think most
accessory apartments would be less than 800 square feet.
I think that
know for an accessory apartment 800 square feet if you had that that would be.
A pretty good sized apartment
you anybody on the Commission got any thoughts on that one way or the other.
>> My
thought is that
800 square feet is like a
one bedroom apartment.
If you're going go out and look for apartments in an apartment building,
that's not a very big
thing. Would think that you'd want to allow the 800 and
figure it's gonna be at least that size.
Okay.
>> Our
in law apartment on our house is 800 square feet and it's not real big.
>> Do you know what your square footage is on your house, Anne?
>> The rest of the house, it's about between two thousand four hundred and two thousand six hundred.
>> Okay, so if we took
one third of the 2,400,
that would give you the 800.
Yeah.
So that,
even if we went with
the thousand square feet, if you took the third of yours, and yours is a good sized house,
that would limit you right now to about
800 square feet.
Then I think We went to the max. Yep, and most people do.
And that's okay.
We just have to make sure that we're
happy with it. But my
sense would be we
could copy the state
things in there Certainly
can't nobody's gonna
nobody can fault us for using the words that the state provided.
>> Yeah,
like that approach
and that gives you the flexibility to go to a thousand square feet. Yep, it does if you had a
>> 3,000 square foot house.
Right.
Our next
little bullet point here says it must contain kitchen, sanitary facilities,
and living quarters.
And
on the state recommendation,
it has cooking facilities.
I like what we have now better.
Yeah.
Because
I don't know about you, but I had cooking facilities in my college dorm room. Yeah. We didn't have microwaves back there, we had hot pots.
And so I was cooking hot dogs and cooking soup.
And
I think what we really want is
a small kitchen.
And so my recommendation would be to
>> leave the words that we got there. How do we define that though? Does it have to have a sink and a
cooktop or how do we define kitchen?
>> I
could certainly add some words in there that further define it,
that it has a kitchen sink
and
refrigerator,
stove.
I don't know. What does everybody think about that?
I think the public health code might address that.
Yeah, check into that.
>> Can you check-in for me, Jim? I have a hard time working my way through the public health stuff there.
Jed, can I make a comment?
Yes.
>> Okay. So two things. One, you asked initially whether the assessor's card
lists net or gross
floor area.
The assessor's card
lists
essentially
for area derived by outside dimensions,
that is gross
floor area. So
that's one piece of information,
the second thing is kind of one of the biggest.
If your goal in this is to provide affordable housing,
the first thing you can do to make it affordable
is to make it relatively
small.
Houses scale and cost with size.
So, but when they get super small, they get expensive again,
which is why the original regulations had that size limit,
because two fifty square feet is about the smallest size you could build without going to specialty,
you know, super narrow kitchen stoves and things of that nature. So, was why you as a commission may choose to change that, but that's, that was the rationale for and that's all I got. Okay thank you Eric.
>> I think Eric you know just hit on a good point we've got you know everybody sees on TV now these tiny houses
If
you built something like that, would that qualify as an accessory dwelling?
>> So
interesting that, well,
there's a line in our affordable housing plan
and it talks about
housing
facilities for
care providers.
And it's talking about the little trailers that you can bring in.
And
while I didn't know it,
I bet we because we didn't opt out of that,
we
fit under that category that somebody can bring a little trailer in if it's for,
you know, a caregiver.
I haven't heard about that.
I think the tiny house would be an appropriate
accessory dwelling unit. Nobody says it has to be on top of a garage or any of that kind of thing. That's
absolutely
essential,
or essential to,
and consistent with the goal of increasing affordable housing for the young folks.
My
son, when he first
started working, lived in an
accessory dwelling unit. Probably wasn't called that. It was called a modified garage at that point in time.
And if you think back, Yofanzi on Happy Days lived in
an accessory apartment, you know, and it probably was
a room over a garage or something. But
no, I think the tiny house thing, if somebody wanted to build that,
that
would be a
great
use of that.
And
so good point. Then the $250
is that,
should we lower that number?
>> I think we should just,
think,
I'll check with Attorney Branch. I didn't want to hold him around for this discussion here.
I think he would tell us that putting a minimum square footage in this is illegal.
You know, our regulations right now, for the reasons that Eric mentioned earlier,
specify a minimum square footage for a house of 500 square feet. We've
been told that
that is no longer legal.
I don't know if it was legal when we put it in there or not, but it's not legal now. And so my thought is if you can't have a minimum size for a house, you probably can't have a minimum size for an accessory apartment.
So I'm going to go continue on down to the next one here.
Our regulations say site plan for an internal accessory apartment special permit for detached.
The state is going, they want to make this easy. It's as of right site plan approval.
And I'm okay with that for these things. I think, you know, when you talk about the room over the garage or the tiny house or any of that,
I'm okay with doing that and making that
easy, which the state is trying to force us to. We're not doing a very good job of getting that affordable housing in town. We need more of it and
this would help us do that. Anybody else have thoughts on that?
>> No, I agree with you, Jed. That makes a lot of sense.
Okay.
>> I talked about parking spots. We say one additional parking space for a total of three with a common driveway.
Jim had mentioned to me, well, what about if you're already on a common driveway, you put the accessory dwelling unit?
I think with
an accessory apartment,
my understanding of a common driveway
is not a shared driveway,
it's common.
Whoever's in the accessory apartment parks next to your garage
just like you do, and you don't necessarily have
anything else going there.
The state talks about one additional parking space
for the accessory apartment, kind of same as us.
The state talks about authorized for any lot that contains a single family dwelling.
Right now,
size is 60,000
square feet.
And this size is really
the thing that got me wanting to make the change because
we did turn down
an apartment
on a guy who was a 40,000 square foot lot.
I was going to go down, I thought it was easy to say, okay, go down to a 40,000 square foot,
and then Jim mentioned somebody might be putting in an application for
a lot that's a little less than an acre. And that's when I started looking at what is over in the town center area. And there's some smaller ones here.
But in an effort to increase
the
affordable housing,
I'm sort of okay with any lot that can get the health code to pass.
You
know, if you've got a little lot and you want to fill it up with something else and you meet the setback requirements and you meet the percentage
of the lot that you covered,
okay, you know, if you meet all those other wickets,
I can
live without a size requirement.
So. I
>> have a question to do with, we opted out of the
part of this because of the lot sizes down at the lake being small,
but
those lots probably wouldn't meet the requirements of
the setback and the space
on the lot for that. So,
we really need to do that opting out? You know, it seems like the other requirements wouldn't have been met, so.
>> My
desire to opt out in the Lake District
was
I don't think the Health District
has the oomph in their regulations
to
protect the lake.
They do pretty much a paperwork review of a septic system
and
don't get into whether it's functioning or any of that kind of stuff.
Because I couldn't convince myself that the health code would protect the lake,
chose to opt out.
That was,
know, Attorney Branch,
you know, said that we should opt out for a number of reasons.
Okay. Being only one of them, and so we did.
I did not know about these little lots over in the town center until within the last month or so.
Right. And so I thought, the smallest lot we had outside Lake District was probably an acre.
No, it's probably smaller than some other places too. Yep, and if there are, I'm not aware of it, but
I only stumbled into
these
because I was looking after I heard that 12 Center Street was not an acre lot.
But anyhow,
>> Somebody somebody else when you were going through this list,
The town sanitarian certified,
is that septic?
Or what is that for?
>> That is the
Eastern Highlands Health District has to certify
the septic plan. For building
accessory apartment,
they're not going to put in another septic system. They're just going to tap in,
whether it's internal to the house or external, they'll just tap into the existing septic system,
is adding an extra bedroom capability in
all that.
Okay, thank you.
>> Okay,
So,
Eric,
I'm going to go out of sequence
here.
This is from the
assessor's card for my house.
And
I think,
you know, I've got
not a huge house.
And, you know, for living space,
it lists that I've got about 1,800 square feet.
And that's probably pretty close.
So
I think this is what equates to net
area.
If
I look at the gross area, which they have it listed as gross area here,
I got over 6,000 square feet.
And that's because
I've got an unfinished basement. I've got my attic. I don't think any of it's got more than the seven foot ceiling
up there that's required to make it count as living space.
So I got some attic, I got some basement, I got some
you know, porch and I got a bunch of decking and that so
it makes a difference whether we're talking
net or gross.
Wow.
>> Then
in Section 24 of our regs, we've got a definition
of gross floor area
and it says floor area shall include basements,
you know, some restrictions there, attic space more than seven and a half feet,
Roof, porches, breezeways,
mezzanines,
it's got garages in here.
So anyhow, that's how you and that's what that's what comes up with that big number that I've got on
my card.
In section 11, which discusses
sizes of lots and setbacks and all that stuff,
it has this line in here, in computing gross floor area, customary rooms such as hallways,
stairways, closets shall be included.
The following shall not be included. And here's a bunch of stuff that were included
on that definition from Section 24.
So, there's a little inconsistency
in our regulations
there.
And then if you look in Section 24
about the net floor area,
it's very consistent with what's in Section 11 for the gross floor area.
And so, while I'm not looking to change section 11 at this point,
if we changed in the
regulation
on accessory apartments to
net floor area, which is the words that the state uses,
that
gets rid of all these things like garages,
you know, and stuff that
shouldn't be included there.
So, anyhow, that would be my recommendation to go back to the net floor area where if we use the net floor area
that our definitions say works and it's consistent with Section 11 of our regulations.
So I've been wrestling with that a little bit there.
One more thing that Jim and I have kicked around a little bit just to be
I can see it coming up
where
it says the gross floor area of accessory units shall be between 800 square feet
between two fifty and eight hundred and shall be less than 33%
of the gross floor area of the single family dwelling.
And so the next question I have would be,
let's say that the single
is the single family dwelling this box here
or is it this whole box here?
And so if
the whole
thing is 1,000 square feet, you take a third of it, that gives you three thirty three square feet here, six sixty six square feet there,
and that would be that.
Or if you looked at
one third of the six sixty six, now you're down to a really tiny, tiny room.
And I think
leaving the latitude to make that as big as possible
makes sense.
So anyhow,
don't know,
I just,
Jim and I are, you know, there's always going to be things
that the regulations
don't cover,
and that's why we have the Commission.
Can take a look. Does it comply with our regulations?
More or less, yes, no, and makes sense and all that kind of stuff.
But that was one of the other gotchas I got.
So anyhow,
from
my assessor's guard,
if we took one third of the 6,000 square feet, could have a 2,000 square foot accessory apartment.
Or if I took one third of the 1,800, that's five forty. A little on the small side, but my house isn't
a huge one either.
Jim and I talked about,
so a guy puts in a three car garage and the three car garage built over it has,
you know, lots of square footage.
How's he going to get his accessory apartment in there?
Maybe
if he wants an accessory apartment, he doesn't get to have
a three car garage. He only gets a two car garage if he wants to use the whole upstairs. Or if he has the roof slope down and takes it off,
can do that. But we're going to come through a bunch of issues that we can't foresee,
can't put them into regulations,
and we'll deal with those at the time comes.
So after listening to any of that,
do folks think I'm on the right track, off the right track?
Did I send I bet you I didn't even send changes to this section out to anybody. I sent you a lot of stuff to read, but probably not this one.
Okay, we'll hold that thought for a minute.
I'm going show you one more thing before we close this out. That's a definition of lot frontage, as we had talked about.
And in section five point five point seven point six, I forget what this is,
It's in the open space and development densities. Frontage means frontage on a public street that either exists currently
or is proposed as part of the subdivision.
And I was originally,
you know, back when we were talking about frontage, was just going to include that in the definition section and make that our definitions.
As I looked online,
Googling definitions
of frontage,
there was, you know, one little caveat that I thought was worth putting in,
and it talked about if you got a corner lot,
your frontage can include that distance on both roads.
I guess there could be a lot.
There could be a lot where you have a road on the front and you have a road on the back.
And then maybe you only got half the desired frontage if we were to do that.
Not sure. Anybody got any thoughts on the
frontage definition?
>> Good. I'm
a little unclear.
Are we suggesting that for any fee measured
at the street line and do we have a definition of street line?
Is
it the edge of the property
measured?
>> We do not.
So
I went back to Pine Ridge.
Yep. And on that particular lot,
we had to go the distance along the street
to get the required frontage for the rear lots
because it added a little curvature.
And at the time we were discussing it, we said that was okay.
So if we were to have taken the distance
perpendicular to the driveway sides and measured across,
he would not have had the required
frontage.
So that's why we put distance along the public street,
which
is consistent with
on a public street here. That doesn't mean necessarily back where the right of way is because I did not want to get into where is the right of way. We have a hard time figuring out how wide is the right of way on a bunch of streets. I figured I'd make it easy. You measure it along the street and if you got the required frontage, you're good to go.
We can make it.
We can make it different than that, but that was my thought.
Does that clear it up at all, Jim?
>> I'm thinking it through. Mean, the only.
There's only a difference if there's a radius in the road.
Yep.
Okay.
>> Yeah, I think it's clear. Okay, and maybe down here we should specify
frontage on a corner lot may contain distance along the street on multiple sides of the lot. I'm not sure we want to allow that guy who
right now, you know, there is a lot or two on
Lake Road and Lakeside Drive
that have frontage on both.
We
probably don't want to have half the frontage. We probably want all the frontage
on one street.
Or we can cross out the corner too. You either got it on the
front of your lot or you don't. I
can go either way. I just reviewed other
definitions of frontage and saw that was included in it.
I like your proposed definition as is.
>> Okay, anybody else have thought?
Okay, so what I'm going to do is I'm going to include
this definition in that section 24
that we're going to take to public hearing on January 23. Jim, I'll put
that into the chain so you can send it out to everybody else
soon to get the municipality
review.
And then
nothing means that we can't, you know, we can change these definitions
at the meeting where we go to approve them at, which is going to be on hopefully the twenty third.
And
that'd be that.
Okay. January 23, I'm talking. Yep.
>> Jed, once again,
can I bite Ben? You can. Okay.
Two things. One, since we
have changed our regulations
from R40 to the air deed design. One
of the options you could have
is set the minimum
side lot size to loud accessory dwelling unit
as that
that's allowed under the conservation subdivision regulations,
which would be a 30,000
square foot lot.
So that would be one option
that gets you beyond the problem you have of the existing lots
not qualified yet still putting some kind of minimum
on it.
The second thing is I put in the chat box,
a picture of one of the accessory dwelling units
that's
put out by Lindahl, Cedar Homes,
so you can see kind of the style and what you can do in a really small accessory dwelling unit.
That's it. Just information.
And I'll shut up again. Okay.
>> No. I appreciate it. It's good to have you here, Eric, and
and I appreciate
all of that.
So,
bear with me, I'm getting to the end here.
So, anyhow, this you have not seen. I will send it out soon. I thought
I already sent out too much stuff for this one.
But as we go down, it's really pretty easy.
I crossed out the words to provide for the needs of the elderly.
When
we started out, that's what we were looking at for accessory apartments. I think,
know,
now
it's just as much for the new kids starting out as it is for the elderly.
And so I just
to fulfill an increasing need for smaller affordable housing units.
So,
I thought that was pretty easy to get through.
Down here, we put
site plan review and standards.
You know, right now it's for units located within the principal dwelling or detached from the principal dwelling.
Either way, that's consistent with the state.
I sometimes ask myself if the
accessory dwelling unit is going to be internal to a dwelling,
why does
it even need to come to the Commission? And
I don't have a good answer for that. I just wasn't willing to have it not come to the Commission for site plan review yet. Maybe at some point in time we get there, but
it seemed consistent with the state that it would come to the Commission for site plan review and that would be that.
I put the setback requirement to section 11.2,
space requirements are satisfied for the accessory apartment.
I did that because that eliminated
the discussion of that minimum
lot size
in there being 60,000 square feet and
having to wrestle with that if we put the setback requirements now that
that's no longer applicable.
Although we can, know, just like we have for the Lake District, it says 120,000
square feet, as Eric was mentioning, we could specify
a lot of at least 30,000 square feet right
there in the introductory section.
I changed gross to net. I thought that was consistent with what we were looking.
No larger than 800 square feet and shall be no larger
than 33
of the net floor area.
So I think we had talked maybe about making that a thousand.
I can change that.
I think that was the intention of the commission there is to
go up to a thousand if you had a big enough house to allow that.
And I'll make that change.
In addition, the accessory apartment
shall not alter the basic character of the dwelling as a single family residence consistent with the character of the surrounding buildings.
It does not distract from the rural characteristics of the area.
I have a hard time
figuring out
what would distract from the rural characteristics of the area, but certainly,
you know, if somebody had
the Fred Flintstone house or something that I've seen out in Los Angeles,
that might not be
in keeping with the rural characteristics of the town. That's
fairly
standard verbiage there,
but it
makes the accessory apartment should
blend in with the neighborhood not not
be.
Something.
I don't know I guess we'll we'll recognize it when we see it.
And that's why the Commission, this is about the only thing that the Commission really gets to decide
is whether or not it's consistent with the character, the rural characteristic of the town.
Then they got rid of all the special permit stuff.
So
what I'd like to do,
Jim, did we goof up by me not having an application for this one here?
Yes.
>> There
you go.
So how do we get out of that so that we can meet
a, and if we can't, that's fine.
I was just hoping to include this with the public hearing on
January 23 as well. But if we can't do it,
we'll
just do another public hearing
sometime after that when we
do everything.
I can't think of way off yet. Okay.
>> So, I will not so I will send this out to everybody to take a look at after I make a couple of changes to it.
But I will not plan on doing that at the January 23 meeting. I'll figure out
there's more changes that we can make and
it'll make for another public hearing later on down the road. I want to make sure that we go just as fast as possible to get,
you know, Eric's
changes in there to support the
community center.
So that
will be that.
That's all I wanted to talk about for accessory apartments.
Jed, I have a couple questions.
Yep, go ahead, Leanne.
>> I
guess I'm still unclear
about
how much we can actually change from what the state said and what we're saying about minimum
size of these apartments. It's been mentioned anywhere from two fifty square feet to 800 square feet. And I guess I'm not clear as to
what we can do and what we're saying we might want to do.
>> Okay.
So when we opted out, the state
gave us lots of
guidance
that they hoped would turn into regulations
on accessory apartments.
There was one small portion of that that
we
didn't like,
But when we chose to opt out because of those small lots in Lake District,
the process
opted us out from all the state guidance.
So we do not need to comply with any of the state
recommendations.
Okay. I was
not satisfied
with the fact that
currently,
at least I and the Commission, at least at one point,
determined that somebody on a one acre lot couldn't put in an accessory apartment.
I was hoping to change our regulations so that that
issue was not in there.
If the state has some recommendations
that are better than what we have that we like better, gives us an opportunity to change it.
If we wanted
to have a minimum square foot size for an accessory apartment, which we currently have two fifty square feet,
I would have to get feedback from Attorney Branch on my
thought is that is no longer legal, but
I could get his cut on that if we wanted to do that.
You mean any minimum is no longer legal?
Correct.
Okay.
So, are we putting
a percent
>> or a figure in here or are we just not doing anything with it right now? We are going to do both. We will use either 800 or 1,000 and I thought the consensus from the commission was a thousand.
As a minimum? That would be a maximum.
Max, okay.
>> And
the other size thing is
33%
of one third of the net
principal dwelling square footage.
And
so again, this gets us if you had a 2,000 square foot house,
33%
would be
six
sixty six square foot accessory apartment,
which is smaller than 1,000 so your maximum size would be six sixty six square feet.
It would be the smaller those two things.
>> We're saying that as a percent and we're also saying that 1,000 square
feet is the maximum?
>> Yes.
So
you've got a maximum of 33
of your existing square footage
or
1,000 feet, whichever is smaller.
Okay.
Any other questions?
>> Can you do the reverse? So
I have a thousand square foot house. If we're talking net dimensions,
I have basically a thousand square foot house.
Can I build a 3,000 square foot house on it and just claim my house as the accessory dwelling unit?
>> I'm sure you could.
Yep, that'd be great news for the town.
I got no problem with that.
>> I had another question. It sounds like what Eric is saying about
a number four.
It starts out with the words require setback. Sorry, Eric, were you through?
Yep.
>> Okay.
It
says require setback lot size and building frontage less than or equal to that which is required for principal dwelling,
comma, and require lot coverage greater than or equal to that which is required for the principal dwelling.
So does require
lot coverage mean that you could build
an accessory dwelling larger than your principal dwelling?
No.
That's not what we just said, but
>> What
Eric was saying is
he would rebuild
to make the principal dwelling 3,000 square feet.
They're
making his
current house, which is 1,000 square feet,
the accessory apartment.
Okay. So he was building out,
which
sort of makes sense to me.
Fact, I've seen that done on Columbia Lake. Was
a lot as I drive up Erdoni Road and it had
the initial house
they turned into,
well initially it was an
apartment over a three car garage.
And I thought that was a plenty big house and they built this huge
house on there. Now I haven't looked at Columbia's
accessory apartment regulations,
but they did exactly what Eric was just suggesting.
Any other questions on the accessory apartments?
And again, we won't tackle those on this next go around. We'll hold those in advance. But that's
I want to start putting those in the
pile to do on
the non urgent
basis there going forward. And we'll do it right.
I'll get the application in there so that we can follow the rules.
Okay. I am going to try.
Everybody see the town website now?
Okay.
Everybody see the minutes from
September 19 meeting?
Yes.
>> Okay, these were
revised from what we had initially
posted on
our website.
But I will make a motion to approve
the meeting minutes of September
as presented.
Second.
Any
>> discussion on
these minutes?
And I probably didn't send those out to you
either, so I don't know if everybody
found them online.
We are
not all that new.
But anyhow,
does anybody have any comments on the meeting minutes?
And I have got three.
So Carol Ann, the comments are
under the alternates.
In addition to Ann Blanchard, Kevin Arneson attended that meeting.
Under Item five was really
new business, Item six was old business.
And down here where it says Jed Larson stated it is mixed use.
I actually stated it was zoned R60.
Now, R60 isn't really what
the zone is. The zone is actually the ARD,
but when I looked at the
video because I knew I didn't say it was mixed use,
I said it was R60, so that's what the minutes should reflect.
And that
was all the comments I had
on that.
Anybody else have any comments?
>> Hearing none? I have a question. I wasn't there,
but it appears that
you must have seated an alternate that day.
>> I did seat an alternate that day.
And the alternate,
I think was Ann Blanchard. Is that correct, Ann?
Yes, it was. Yep. So
>> thank you, Susan. We
should also include that
Ann Blanchard was
seated.
Okay, any other discussion?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Steve?
Leigh Ann?
I abstain.
I was absent.
>> And Susan was absent. Right.
But I vote
aye.
So the motion passes
three zero two
with
Lee
Ann
Hutchinson
and Susan England abstaining.
And then,
just for
your information,
Carol Ann,
normally we have seen at the end of the meeting minutes,
it says
submitted by and then your name, so we know who's on there.
Since
a little
since we didn't have that, I'm not going to put somebody else's name in there
saying that it's signed by them when they're not here.
That's just for your information going forward. I'd like to have
the minutes
acknowledging that
they're by you.
Okay, thank you.
>> That gets us up to
the
most recent meeting, which was Monday, October 17, and
I will make
a motion
to accept the meeting minutes from the planning and zoning meeting on Monday, October 17, as presented.
Second.
>> Thank you, Steve.
Any comments on
these minutes?
And up in the under members present,
we should have
alternates present.
And Anne Blanchard, I think you were in attendance at that meeting, were you not?
Yes, I was, but I was not seated.
>> Right.
So you were there but not seated because we had the full commission, but we should still acknowledge your presence at the meeting.
Then one typo here on page two,
Jed Larson presented the
letter, not latter.
And that was all I had. Any other
members have any other comments on
the meeting minutes?
>> Jed, under the public speak,
should we mention that Jerry submitted a letter as well?
Oh, it does say that for taking on the Board of Education's letter. Okay, I got it. Okay.
>> Any other comments?
Hearing none, I'll call for a vote. Anne?
Aye.
Steve?
Leigh Ann?
Aye.
Susan?
>> I abstain because that was not there. And I vote aye as well. Motion passes
four-zero-one
with Susan England abstaining.
Next up, Jim, is correspondence.
None.
Okay. Administrative
reports.
>> Enforcement action. I am working with
Mr. Barnett on Route 6 to both
clean up this property, which is an ongoing
activity, well as an
order was issued to vacate
a trailer on the property where there was
a number of occupants
and working with the health department on that to get those folks
out of there in a timely fashion.
Other than that, have.
I do need to
work with
Dennis
O'Brien, the town attorney on on a follow-up on a citation that was issued a few months back
with an ongoing.
Fines other than that, it's about all I have right now.
Hopefully I I do have some other enforcement actions to take. Hopefully I'll have more time
in the next
month or two.
>> Okay.
Now, is the
action you're taking on the gravel pit, that's an enforcement action, is it not?
It is. Okay.
>> And as I looked on
the website,
I did not find your letter
to Mr. Genovese under the enforcement actions. I did see your letter to Mr. Barnett.
Okay, I can get that on there. Yep.
Anything else under your administrative report, Jim?
No.
Okay.
Jim, can
I ask a question?
Absolutely.
>> Jim, on the Center Street property,
I noticed that there's a big drop off into the
foundation area now since they removed So the
I'm wondering, do we have any requirements that they
put fencing around there or at least tape mark off the area? So I'm worried that kids could fall into there or somebody
can get hurt.
>> I'm.
Pretty certain it's a it's a building code issue. I will bring it to the attention of the building
enforcement officer.
I can ask him.
I I should.
I have been trying to take keep an eye on that. I haven't been there in awhile.
You know it's not great. I did expect him to move forward with an application
to build their home, but he hasn't as of yet. I I will take a look at that. That should That shouldn't be a problem to take care of. Thank you. Good
>> point, Steve. Thanks for bringing that up.
The Inland Wetlands
liaison,
we did not have a meeting last month, so therefore there is nothing to report.
Moving on to Item 10, public speak.
Hearing none, I'll go to the next regularly scheduled meeting is
Monday, December 19.
>> Sorry,
I'm late. Can I just poke in one thing again? You bet. You
know, we, you keep talking about there's no lower limit on the building
size.
Yep.
There is a limit, but it's only the limit applied
by the health code, which I think works out to somewhere around 150
square feet, like that.
Okay.
That's what the
state says
is the minimum.
>> And that's pretty minimal.
And I think as we were
struggling to
get the recording going at the start,
I had the very first thing on my note list to welcome Carol Ann as our new board clerk.
And I think in our enthusiasm to get the recording going, I missed right over that. But it's nice to have you with us, Carol Ann. Thank you. Thank you. I enjoyed it. I enjoyed it. You
know, look
at the last meeting minutes as a good example of the kind of things
to put in the meeting. You know, it's not going to be a regurgitation of everything we do. The clerks have pretty much done a good job of getting,
you know, what's
important and putting it in there.
You mean I can't refer
>> we go along, ask Jim or me,
we'll be happy to
>> help make you as successful as we can. Thank you. I I can't refer to the Fonz apartment
The
>> minutes, but you can. I thought that was pretty clever. Fonzie was ahead of his time.
That's right. So many things.
>> Yeah, well, thank you. Thank you very much. Caroline, I will work with you on filing them this. The filing this chatter minutes is a little different because you're replacing and we'll do whatever the town clerk wants. Quite honestly.
Okay, we'll talk on that. Thank you. How that would be handled.
>> I will defer to her. Thank you. Okay, So the last order of business is for everybody to have a wonderful Thanksgiving.
And
we'll see you
next month just before Christmas.
So thank you all for attending and participating and giving feedback
and all that. And I'll make a motion to adjourn.
Come on, Steve, don't break your record. Second.
You, happy Thanksgiving.
>> Yep.
Motion passes five-zero-zero.
Thank you everybody and good night. Good night. Good night.